# SIPENG ZHENG

Website: https://zhengsipeng.github.io Email: zhengsipeng@ruc.edu.cn Cellphone: 15905058181

### RESEARCH INTEREST

My research interest focuses on human behavior understanding and its application in embodied AI. Relevant tasks what I'm interested in includes visual relation detection, scene graph generation, action recognition as well as multi-modal learning and multi-modal pre-training for the above tasks. In addition to these tradition vision and language tasks, recently, I'm exploring how to apply multi-modal pre-training for embodied AI area such as manipulation, which plays a key role in applications like robotics, meta-world and etc.

## **EDUCATION**

Ph.D in Computer Science	Sep. 2018 - Jun. 2023 Advisor: Qin Jin
Information Institute of Renmin University of China B.S in Computer Science	Sep. 2014 - Jun. 2018 Advisor: Qin Jin
EXPERIENCE	
Research Internship at MSRA Multimedia Searching and Mining Group	Feb. 2022 - Present
Research Internship at Beijing Academy of Artificial Intelligence Multi-modal and Multi-lingual Large-scale Pre-train	Sep. 2021 - Jun. 2022
Research Internship at BianLiFeng	Apr. 2017 - Oct. 2017

### RESEARCH PROJECTS

## Multi-modal Pre-training for Motor Control

Apr. 2022 - Present

0010

2020

- By regarding offline reinforcement learning on motor control as sequence prediction, I study how multi-modal representations pre-trained on diverse ego-centric videos can greatly improve downstream robotic manipulation tasks. The work is under review in NeurIPS 2022 (1st author).
- Current embodied AI of robotic manipulation is limited to simple scenes (e.g., on a workbench) and single tasks. To avoid this, the agent is required to not only provide timely feedback to complex environments, but also understand complex instructions. We aim to explore multi-modal large-scale pre-trained models in interaction scenarios of real life in addition to traditional understanding tasks. This work is target at CVPR 2023 (co-author).

## Temporal Sentence Grounding of Long-form Videos

Jan. 2021 - Present

- Most existing models of thi task follow a two-stage pipeline, that is, first extracts the features of video key frames, and then performs multi-modal fusion between the extracted video and language embeddings. However, this non-E2E approach has two drawbacks. First, there is a large domain gap between extracted visual features and downstream data. Second, such pipeline ignores fine-grained spatial cues. Considering this, we propose an end-to-end framework, which is target at CVPR 2023 (1st author)
- Grounding the location of a sentence in an untrimmed video can be actually regarded as a matching problem between video clips and sentences. However, the speech-to-noise ratio between visual and language modalities naturally does not match (language's is much higher than video's generally). Considering such mismatch, we propose an adaptive multi-scale local attention mechanisms, which is under review in EMNLP 2023 (co-author).

## Multi-modal Video Relation Detection

Nov. 2021 - Apr. 2022

• I build a robust relation system with a temporal-aware relational predictor and improve the tracking module with better efficiency in multi-person scenarios, which is ranked 2nd in **ACM MM** Video Relation Understanding Grand Challenge. Then I propose the first end-to-end transformer-based model for video relation detection, which is distinct from previous multi-stage pipeline and is published in **CVPR 2022 Oral** (1st author).

## Multi-modal Image Relation Understanding

Jun. 2018 - Present

- Image Relation Detection. I propose a multi-level attention method to fuse multiple modalities (i.e. visual appearances, spatial locations, textual semantics) for relation prediction, which is published in ACM MM 2019 (1st author).
- Human-Object Interaction (HOI) The HOI task only focuses on the relation between human and objects. I propose a graph-based method to effectively utilize human skeletons for fine-grained human-object relation prediction, which is published in ICME 2020. I also notice that the HOI task has long been plagued by the lack of data and supervision due to the large number of possible combinations of verbs and objects in real life. Models trained on limited data can only predict HOIs within a set of fixed categories. We therefore propose an open-category HOI pre-training model with specially designed proxy tasks that can well generalize to novel interaction categories. This work is under review in NeurIPS 2022 (1st author).

## Few-shot Action Recognition

Dec. 2020 - Aug. 2021

0000

2015

• I propose a hierarchical matching approach to project videos into a metric space and classify videos via nearest neighboring, which supports comprehensive similarity measure at global, temporal and spatial levels. To avoid the lack of supervisions on fine-grained spatio-temporal matching, we propose a hierarchical contrastive learning algorithm. This work is published in **ECCV 2022** (1st author).

## **PUBLICATION**

- 1. **Sipeng Zheng**, Shizhe Chen, and Qin Jin. Few-shot action recognition with hierarchical matching and contrastive learning. In *ECCV*, 2022
- 2. **Sipeng Zheng**, Shizhe Chen, and Qin Jin. Vrdformer: End-to-end video visual relation detection with transformers. In *CVPR*, pages 18836–18846, 2022
- 3. **Sipeng Zheng**, Shizhe Chen, and Qin Jin. Skeleton-based interactive graph network for human object interaction detection. In *ICME*, pages 1–6, 2020
- 4. **Sipeng Zheng**, Shizhe Chen, and Qin Jin. Visual relation detection with multi-level attention. In *ACM MM*, pages 121–129, 2019
- 5. **Sipeng Zheng**, Xiangyu Chen, Shizhe Chen, and Qin Jin. Relation understanding in videos. In *ACM MM*, page 2662–2666, 2019

#### AWARDS

* Ranked 3rd (currently), Facebook ECCV 2022 Ego4D Natural Language Query Challenge.	2022
$\star$ Ranked 3th in Facebook CVPR 2022 Ego4D Natural Language Query Challenge.	2022
$\star$ Ranked 4th, NIST TRECVID 2021 Ad-hoc Video Search (AVS) Challenge. (20+ teams)	2021
$\star$ Ranked 4th in CVPR 2021 HOMAGE Scene-graph Generation Challenge.	2021
* Ranked 2th in ACM MM 2020 Video Relationship Understanding Grand Challenge.	2020

- $\star$  Ranked 2nd and won the Best Method Prize in ACM MM 2019 Video Relationship Understanding Grand Challenge.
- ★ First Class Scholarship for Ph.D Students. 2018-2021
- \* First Prize in National University Mathematical Modeling Competition.

# **SERVICE**

★ Conference Reviewer for C	VPR, ICCV, ECCV, NeurIPS, ACM MM, ICME, etc.	
$\star$ Teaching Assistant	Introduction to the Theory of Computation	2020
$\star$ Teaching Assistant	Probability and Statistics	2019
$\star$ Teaching Assistant	Spoken Language Processing	2018

# PARTICIPATED GRANTS

- $\star$  National Key Research and Development Plan No. 2016YFB1001202 (Computational Principles of Human-Computer Interaction)
- ★ Beijing Natural Science Foundation No. 4192028 (Language Understanding and Interaction Based on Auditory Information)